New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice; Records apap012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Issues File, 1971-1984; 9; 3.33 cubic ft.
  The Issues Files were created by the CCJ to collect background information on subjects related to criminal justice reform. The series contains correspondence between Thomas A. Coughlin, Commissioner, and all the New York State central office and facility staff concerning new affirmative action plans. Included are the Commissioners remarks presented to the Assembly Sub-Committee on Affirmative Action in 1980. Also present is information on programs established as alternatives to incarceration 1975-1980, the Attica prisoners 28 demands/convict proposals, along with the correctional guards Union 82 list of demands, and the papers on the legal aftermath of the Attica uprising, mainly concerning the Attica legal defense fund. Also available are newsletters of EUI, [Ending Unnecessary Imprisonment] in New York State, citizen participation (how to) papers, and Christian statements concerning the criminal justice system. A Corrections Information Series for jail classification can also be found concerning background information, court decisions, ACA standards, and examples of classification systems for small, medium, and large prisons. Several other reports can be found on issues such as "Community Alternatives to Maximum Security" 1974-1975, a "Proposal to Repeal New York's Second Felony Offender Law", "Philosophies of Punishment and Correction", "Fines: An Inquiry Into The Use of Fines As an Alternative to Incarceration", "Probation Subsidy", and a summary of the New York State YWCA Intervention Program sponsored by the New York State Commission of Correction. Information related to the expansion of prisons and the prison bond issue intended to fund the expansion including Gov. Plans 1980-1981, Coalition responses and alternatives 1978-1982, Committee hearings 1982, testimony by Coalition members 1981-1982.
  Reports by the Full Step INC. program are also in the series. They address topics of utilization of private sector community correctional organizations, the study of federally sponsored ex-offender community based programs, and the creation of a temporary state commission on transitional services to ex-offenders 1980. Community Correction Acts are included for New York State, 1978, Oregon, 1979, Minnesota, 1973, and Kansas, 1980. These reports also concern community dispute resolution programs in New York State, and information on community service sentences. An important Senate hearing paper can be found concerning Court Consolidation and Appointment vs. Election of Judges. A list of names of those sentenced to execution from the period of 1890-1963 is included along with the crime committed, following is information on the use of the death penalty. Drinking and driving in New York State is also addressed in several reports found in the series, as well as an agenda for the Elderly Criminal Offenders Conference held in 1982. Also found is information from the National Coalition for Jail Reform on inappropriate confinement and information about the creation of Jaycee (Junior Chamber of Commerce) chapters in prisons. The Jaycees are a national leadership training organization for young business men and women. Files on juvenile justice issues can be found mainly concerning youth rights. Other files relate to reducing prison crowding, prison bond folders containing newspaper clippings, prison population planning, racial discrimination in the criminal justice system, sentencing reform, and sex offender programs.
  - Affirmative Action, 1980 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Alternatives to incarceration, 1973-1975; 1980 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Albany Capital Newspapers crime coverage, 1981 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Albany County Jail Sheriff, 1977-1980 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Albany County probation needs, 1979 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Attica aftermath, folder 1, 1971-1975 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Attica aftermath, folder 2, 1976-1981 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Campaign for Ending Unnecessary Imprisonment, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 8)
  - Citizen participation, 1975-1977; 1984 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 9)
  - Child abuse, 1979 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 10)
  - Christian statements on Criminal Justice, 1977-1983 (Box 1 (9-Issues File), Folder 11)
  - Classification of correctional facilities, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Codes Committee - State Legislature, 1982 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Commission on Criminal Sanctions and Justice, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Community Corrections (folder 1), 1973-1975 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Community Corrections (folder 2), 1976-1981 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Community Corrections Full Step, Inc. [Spruill], 1980-1981 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Community Corrections Acts, 1978-1980 (Box 2 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Community Dispute Resolution Programs, 1981-1982 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Community Service Sentences, 1973-1981 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - County jails, 1978-1981 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Court reform, 1979-1980 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Death penalty background (folder 1), 1976-1982 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Death penalty background (folder 2), 1982 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Death penalty opposition, 1977-1981 (Box 3 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Decriminalization of prostitution, 1978-1979 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Domestic compliance with Helsinki Accords: U.S. Prison Conditions, Steven Winter &Robert Nundley, 1982 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Drug related crime, 1983 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Drunk driving, 1980-1981 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Elderly criminal offenders, 1981-1983 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Ex-offender programs, 1977-1979 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Hand-gun control, 1981 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Hook, Robert (see Mandatory Sentencing), Undated (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 8)
  - Impact of 1978 legislation (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 9)
  - Inappropriate confinement-Anne Marie Venne, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 10)
  - Inappropriate confinement - Tess Report, 1978-1980 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 11)
  - Incarceration profile: New York State, 1978-1980 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 12)
  - Jaycees, 1982-1983 (Box 4 (9-Issues File), Folder 13)
  - Jails: Classification Change, 1979 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Jails: Visitation, Undated (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Juvenile justice, 1976-1980 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Letters to Editors - various topics, 1978-1983 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Mandatory Sentencing, 1982 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Marijuana law reform, 1977-1978 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Mediation of disputes, 1980 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Memorandum on proposed legislation, 1980 (Box 5 (9-Issues File), Folder 8)
  - Minimum security jail - articles, 1982 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Minimum sentences - proposed bill, 1980 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous news clips, 1975-1983 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - NAACP Prison Program, 1980-1983 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Netherlands, 1978 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - New York State Task Force on Women, 1983 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Parole reform, 1976-1977 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Ossining takeover, 1983 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 8)
  - Phase Out/Re-entry (Horizon House), 1980-1982 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 9)
  - Police brutality, 1979-1980 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 10)
  - Pre-trial detention, 1980; 1983 (Box 6 (9-Issues File), Folder 11)
  - Prison depopulation program/National Institute of Corrections Grant, 1980-1981 (Box 7 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Prison Bond (folder 1), 1978-1981 (Box 7 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Prison Bond (folder 2), 1981 (Box 7 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Prison Bond (folder 3), 1981-1983 (Box 8 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Prison overcrowding, 1976-1983 (Box 8 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Prison expansion, 1982-1983 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Prisoners' Legal Service, 1981 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Programmes for released prisoners, 1978 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - Pro-active prison population planning, 1971-1982 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Proposals by CCJ, Undated (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Racial discrimination in Criminal Justice, 1978-1980 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
  - Rape: Case of Michael Fair, 1982 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 7)
  - Senate Research Service: "Issues in Focus", 1982 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 8)
  - Sentencing reform, 1974-1983 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 9)
  - Sentencing reform: Mandatory sentencing and Robert Hooks, 1982 (Box 9 (9-Issues File), Folder 10)
  - Sex offender programs (folder 1), 1980-1981 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 1)
  - Sex offender programs (folder 2), 1982 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 2)
  - Statewide Youth Advocacy, 1981-1983 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 3)
  - S.T.O.P. the Olympic Prison (Federal), 1978-1980 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 4)
  - Whiting, James M., Sentencing, 1979-1982 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 5)
  - Victims Assistance Programs, 1982-1983 (Box 10 (9-Issues File), Folder 6)
- Legislation File, 1963-1986; 10; 1.67 cubic ft.
  This series contains analysis of N.Y. State legislation bills by coalition staff and decisions to support or oppose a bill. The series also contains bill monitoring in the assembly and senate 1983-1984, along with bill reporting forms. Many Assembly and Senate bills, along with bill calendars/index can also be found for 1983-1984. Paperwork on opposition to the death penalty for the years of 1979-1984 are also present, lists of Assembly and Senate leaders stating their position on the death penalty, and the 1984 State of the State Message given by Mario M. Cuomo. Insanity defense paperwork by the New York Defenders Association, INC. can be found, along with memorandums of support for several different bills concerning such topics as acts to amend the criminal procedure laws, correctional law, and the penal law etc. The series contains proposed legislation concerning Parole, Permitting Prisoners Serving Life Sentences To Marry, Pre-trial Detention, Probation, Sealing Misdemeanor Records, Victim Compensation Laws, Marijuana Reform, Prison Construction, and Programs For Released Prisoners.
  - Bail, 1979 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 1)
  - Bill analysis forms of Legislative Committee, 1984 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 2)
  - Bill Monitoring Charts Assembly, 1983 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 3)
  - Bill Monitoring Chart Assembly, 1984 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 4)
  - Bill Monitoring Charts Senate, 1983 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 5)
  - Bill Monitoring Charts Senate, 1984 (Box 1 (10-Legislation File), Folder 6)
  - Bill reporting forms/Legislative Committee, Undated (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 1)
  - Bills - Assembly, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 2)
  - Bills and Committee meetings, 1981 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 3)
  - Bills - Senate, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 4)
  - Bills - Senate & Assembly, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 5)
  - Calendar & Index of Bills, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 6)
  - Codes Committee, 1979-1984 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 7)
  - Codes Committee-State Legislature, 1982 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 8)
  - Codes Committee-State Legislature, 1982 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 9)
  - Counter - Budget, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (10-Legislation File), Folder 10)
  - Correctional facility for alcohol-related crimes, 1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 1)
  - Death penalty, 1979; 1981-1982 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 2)
  - Death penalty, 1983-1984 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 3)
  - Death penalty Executive Clemency, 1975-1982 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 4)
  - Death penalty letters of opposition, 1978-1984 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 5)
  - Death Penalty-Opposition, 1977-1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 6)
  - Drug profits law, 1983 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 7)
  - Executive clemency, 1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 8)
  - Governors releases - Crim. Just. budget, 1983-1986 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 9)
  - Insanity defense, 1983-1984 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 10)
  - Legislative contact reports, 11/1983-6/1984 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 11)
  - Lobbying Law negotiations, 1977-1980 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 12)
  - Misdemeanor records, sealing of, 1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 13)
  - New York City, 1980 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 14)
  - Parole, 1980-1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 15)
  - Permitting life sentences to marry, 1981 (Box 3 (10-Legislation File), Folder 16)
  - Memoranda of Support forms - Assembly, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 4 (10-Legislation File), Folder 1)
  - Memorandum of Support forms - Senate, 1983-1984 (Box 4 (10-Legislation File), Folder 2)
  - Memorandum of Support forms: Senate - Assembly, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 4 (10-Legislation File), Folder 3)
  - Proposed Bills, 1977-1978 (Box 5 (10-Legislation File), Folder 1)
  - Sentencing-Reform, 1978-1979 (Box 5 (10-Legislation File), Folder 2)
  - Temporary Release Program, 1975-1979 (Box 5 (10-Legislation File), Folder 3)
  - Victim compensation, 1979 (Box 5 (10-Legislation File), Folder 4)
  - Voting records, 1978 (Box 5 (10-Legislation File), Folder 5)
- Publications File, 1976-1985; 11; 0.67 cubic ft.
  The series contains Updates, 1976-1983, the Coalition's publication which relayed new information through the Rapid Communication Network to all the satellites. Series also includes publications relating to Criminal Justice reform published by the Coalition as well as other organizations, such as A Children's Defense Fund for 1984-1985, The Defender 1979-1983, the newsletter of the New York State Defenders Association, Justicia, the newsletter of the Judicial Process Commission 1979-1980, and Ways & Means a reporter on Innovative Approaches to State and Local Government. Also included is the publication of Thursday's Obligation, this was distributed by Jail Ministry, and a second religious publication, United was the news and information by the Christians United in Mission INC. The series also contained Correctional Services News (1980-1981) and Fortune News (1980-1981).
  - A Children's Defense Budget, 1984-1985 (Box 1 (11-Publications File), Folder 1)
  - The Defender, 1979-1982 (Box 1 (11-Publications File), Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters, 1979-1982 (Box 1 (11-Publications File), Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous reports and articles, Undated (Box 2 (11-Publications File), Folder 1)
  - Publications United, 1981-1983 (Box 2 (11-Publications File), Folder 2)
  - Thursday Obligation, 1980-1983 (Box 2 (11-Publications File), Folder 3)
  - Updates, 1976-1983 (Box 2 (11-Publications File), Folder 4)
  - Ways & Means, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (11-Publications File), Folder 5)